<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
    Document   : TSF.xml
    Created on : 14 décembre 2014, 21:13
    Author     : nguermou
    Description:
        Purpose of the document follows.
-->
<team id="TSF" isCNRS="true">
    <name>Tolérance aux fautes et Sûreté de Fonctionnement Informatique</name>
    <shortName>TSF</shortName>
    <teamMembers>
        <member category="chef d'équipe">
            <lastName>KAANICHE</lastName>
            <firstName>Mohamed</firstName>
            <affiliation>CNRS</affiliation>
            <category>directeur de recherche</category>
        </member>
        <member category="membre permanent">
            <lastName>ALATA</lastName>
            <firstName>Eric</firstName>
            <affiliation>INSA  de Toulouse, LAAS-CNRS</affiliation>
            <category>maître de conférences</category>
        </member>
         <member category="membre permanent">
            <lastName>ARLAT</lastName>
            <firstName>Jean</firstName>
               <affiliation>CNRS </affiliation>     
            <category>Directeur de recherche</category>
        </member>
        <member category="membre permanent">
            <lastName>COLLET</lastName>
            <firstName>Jacques</firstName>
            <affiliations>
                <affiliation> CNRS </affiliation>
            </affiliations>
            <category>Directeur de recherche émérite </category>
        </member>   
    </teamMembers>
    <description>
        <objectives> 
        </objectives>
        <researchTopics>
           <topic>
               <title>
                  Fault prevention
               </title>
               <abstract>
                  The advent of ubiquitous devices and the growing
                  development of location-based services have led to a large scale
                  collection of individuals’ mobility data on a daily basis. Among
                  all the Personally Identifiable Information, learning the location
                  of an individual is one of the major threats against privacy. In
                  order to help location-based services developers to provide privacy-preserving
                  applications, we propose the PROPS protocol, a PRivacy-preserving lOcation Proof
                  System that allows a user to generate a proof of his location in a private way using
                  neighboring nodes as witnesses. The gathered proof can be used to anonymously prove
                  his current or past location.

                  A secure location-based service requires that a mobile user certifies his
                  position before gaining access to a particular resource. Currently, most
                  of existing solutions assume a trusted third party that can vouch for the
                  position claimed by a user. However, as computation and communication
                  capacities become ubiquitous with the large-scale adoption of smartphones
                  by individuals, we propose to leverage on these resources to solve this
                  issue in a collaborative and private manner. We have demonstrated that our
                  protocol provides security properties such as the unforgeability and the
                  non-transferability of the proofs, as well as resistance to classical attacks
                  on such systems like mafia and terrorist frauds.
               </abstract>
            </topic>
              <topic>
               <title>
                  Fault tolerance
               </title>
               <abstract>
                  Recent advances in digital networks and smart sensors and actuators offer new
                  opportunities for the development of innovative fault tolerant architectures
                  for critical control systems that have to satisfy hard dependability,
                  performance and cost reduction requirements. The main issue is to take
                  advantage of the increasing computing capabilities at the sensors and
                  actuators levels to achieve an optimal distribution of systems functionalities
                  and fault tolerance mechanisms among computers and actuators.

                  We have investigated this problem in the context of Flight Control Systems (FCS).
                  We proposed distributed and reconfigurable architectures that break with the
                  traditional COM/MON centralized-federated architectures where specific fault-tolerant
                  computers perform all processing. The new alternative FCS architectures
                  are based on: simplex computers, distribution of system functionalities between computers
                  and actuators, less hardware and software resources while meeting the same (or even better)
                  level of safety and availability requirements as in the prior art. Two architectures have
                  been investigated [3][4]  - the “Massive Voting” (see Figure 1) and the “Priority voting”
                  architectures - validated through respectively OCAS/AltaRica (for safety requirements)
                  and Matlab/Simulink simulations (for robustness requirements). This work was carried out
                  with Airbus-France.
               </abstract>
            </topic>
        </researchTopics>
        <publications>
            <conferences>
                <conference>
                    <title> An approach for the automated analysis of network access controls in cloud computing infrastructures</title>
                    <authors>
                        <author>T.PROBST</author>
                         <author>E.ALATA</author>
                        <author>M.KAANICHE</author>
                        <author>V.NICOMETTE</author>
                    </authors>
                    <conferenceName>NSS</conferenceName>
                    <year>2014</year>
                </conference>
                 <conference>
                    <title>Automatically adjusting concurrency to the level of synchrony</title>
                    <authors>
                        <author>P.FRAIGNIAUD</author>
                        <author>E.GAFNI</author>
                        <author>S.RAJSBAUM</author>
                        <author>M.ROY</author>
                    </authors>
                    <conferenceName>DISC</conferenceName>
                    <year>2014</year>
                </conference>
            </conferences>
            <journals>
                <journal>
                    <title>
                        Heuristical top-k: fast estimation of centralities in complex networks
                    </title>
                    <authors>
                        <author>E.LE MERRER </author>
                        <author> N.LE SCOUARNEC</author>
                        <author>G.TREDAN</author>
                    </authors>
                    <journalName>IPL</journalName>
                </journal>
            </journals>
            <thesises>
              <thesis>
                  <title>Analyse de vulnérabilités de systèmes avioniques embarqués : classification et expérimentation</title>
                  <author>A.DESSIATNIKOFF</author>
                  <year>2014</year>
              </thesis>
            </thesises>
        </publications>
        <partenariat>
            <partner>
                Airbus
            </partner>
             <partner>
                EADS
            </partner>
        </partenariat>
    </description>
</team>
